<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-31T21:54:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pepper and Olive Oil</title><subtitle>Andrew's recipe blog</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Baked Ziti</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/2023/01/31/baked-ziti/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baked Ziti" /><published>2023-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/2023/01/31/baked-ziti</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/2023/01/31/baked-ziti/">&lt;p&gt;This recipe is still something of a draft. Next time I make it I’ll take a picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently learned that it’s possible to make baked pasta dishes without boiling the pasta first.
Instead, just add the dry pasta to the baking dish with extra water and salt, and that water will
cook the pasta as the whole thing bakes. I tried it once, and it works! So, here’s a recipe for
minimal-prep baked ziti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible variations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a bunch of raw baby spinach. No need to sauté first, just stick it in there. But maybe
sautéeing is helpful so the greens wilt a little, otherwise it’s hard to stir them in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chop two eggplants and sauté them in olive oil and salt for 20 minutes until they’re dark and soft.
Mix it in with the rest of the ingredients before baking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For a meaty ziti, use bolognese sauce instead of marinara.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use other pasta shapes according to your whims.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Note: I have not tried this technique on
fresh/raw pasta; it likely won’t work because of the chemical differences. Please tweet at me if
you have info on this!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Entrée" /><summary type="html">This recipe is still something of a draft. Next time I make it I’ll take a picture.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taco Seasoning</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2022/10/14/taco-seasoning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taco Seasoning" /><published>2022-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2022/10/14/taco-seasoning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2022/10/14/taco-seasoning/">&lt;p&gt;Nothing fancy here; this is a good substitute for the stuff in the packet. Make a big batch and keep
it around and toss a couple heaping spoonfuls onto your ground beef.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Sauce" /><summary type="html">Nothing fancy here; this is a good substitute for the stuff in the packet. Make a big batch and keep it around and toss a couple heaping spoonfuls onto your ground beef.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Palestinian Salad</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/middle%20eastern/2022/07/30/palestinian-salad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Palestinian Salad" /><published>2022-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/middle%20eastern/2022/07/30/palestinian-salad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/middle%20eastern/2022/07/30/palestinian-salad/">&lt;p&gt;Outside of the Middle East, this salad is known by various names, most often
“&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli_salad&quot;&gt;Israeli Salad&lt;/a&gt;”, but because I’m
Palestinian I call it “Palestinian Salad”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very simple to make, and a good choice for a hot sunny day! As with most
ubiquitous dishes, there’s no single authoritative recipe. I’ve included some
suggested ingredient swaps below; make it with what you have on hand!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be eaten a myriad of ways. Some serving ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve as a side to any other dish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use as a filler for pita sandwiches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Garnish with sumac or &lt;a href=&quot;/sauce/2020/03/26/tahini-sauce/&quot;&gt;tahini sauce&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eat the whole batch on its own straight from the bowl, like I just did&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Side" /><category term="Middle Eastern" /><summary type="html">Outside of the Middle East, this salad is known by various names, most often “Israeli Salad”, but because I’m Palestinian I call it “Palestinian Salad”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1–2–3 Lentil Soup</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/middle%20eastern/2022/01/14/lentil-soup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1–2–3 Lentil Soup" /><published>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/middle%20eastern/2022/01/14/lentil-soup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/middle%20eastern/2022/01/14/lentil-soup/">&lt;p&gt;I call this “1-2-3” Lentil Soup because it’s an easy way to remember the quantities: &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; onion, &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; carrots, &lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt; cloves of garlic. This recipe is similar to most traditional Arabic recipes for lentil soup; and like any soup you can really do whatever you want and it’ll still taste great. The main difference I’ve seen is that each person likes to use their own particular combination of spices. Some people also add potato for extra heft, but I usually don’t, mostly because it takes more effort, and I think it detracts from the flavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measurements for the spices are approximate and can be easily altered to your personal preference. As with my &lt;a href=&quot;/entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew/&quot;&gt;Beef Stew&lt;/a&gt; recipe, I find the flavor of this soup to be greatly enhanced by the addition of ground coriander. Pre-ground spices are fine, of course, but, if practical, freshly grinding whole seeds will give an extra burst of flavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very easy to make a double or triple batch of this soup; I like to make a big pot and then freeze individual servings, which sets up a simple work-from-home lunch!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Side" /><category term="Middle Eastern" /><summary type="html">I call this “1-2-3” Lentil Soup because it’s an easy way to remember the quantities: 1 onion, 2 carrots, 3 cloves of garlic. This recipe is similar to most traditional Arabic recipes for lentil soup; and like any soup you can really do whatever you want and it’ll still taste great. The main difference I’ve seen is that each person likes to use their own particular combination of spices. Some people also add potato for extra heft, but I usually don’t, mostly because it takes more effort, and I think it detracts from the flavor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ruth’s Pancakes, Remixed</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//breakfast/2020/10/10/ruths-pancakes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ruth’s Pancakes, Remixed" /><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//breakfast/2020/10/10/ruths-pancakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//breakfast/2020/10/10/ruths-pancakes/">&lt;p&gt;I like pancakes. They’re wonderful when dressed with a wide variety of toppings, such as maple syrup, nuts, or fruit compotes. The only breakfast food I like more than pancakes are waffles.
On the other hand, I’m not a morning person, so a good pancake recipe has to be &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt;. I want to be able to roll out of bed and make delicious pancakes with as little prep as possible. This is one such recipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the various pancake recipes I’ve made, this one has two defining factors: it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; rich (thanks to the generous amount of butter), and it doesn’t require buttermilk. It’s very easy to make, and, due to its buttery richness, it’s my go-to recipe when breakfast is to be a special occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit for the recipe goes to Ruth Reichl, chef, food critic, and author of multiple cookbooks. Her recipe uses &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of butter, so much that I can get through only a couple pancakes before feeling overwhelmed. I’ve slightly reduced the original amount of butter to a point where they’re still delicious but not knock-you-off-your-chair rich. I’ve also increased the portion size to be enough for three people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested toppings:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apples or pears, sautéed in butter and cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blueberry compote (combine berries, sugar, and flour in a saucepan, cook until thick)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maple syrup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chopped almonds or walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Ruth Reichl, adapted by Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Breakfast" /><summary type="html">I like pancakes. They’re wonderful when dressed with a wide variety of toppings, such as maple syrup, nuts, or fruit compotes. The only breakfast food I like more than pancakes are waffles. On the other hand, I’m not a morning person, so a good pancake recipe has to be easy. I want to be able to roll out of bed and make delicious pancakes with as little prep as possible. This is one such recipe.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tahini Sauce</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2020/03/26/tahini-sauce/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tahini Sauce" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2020/03/26/tahini-sauce</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2020/03/26/tahini-sauce/">&lt;p&gt;This sauce is so simple it doesn’t really lend itself to a formal recipe, but I still have to tell you how to make it somehow and this blog template formats every page as a recipe whether I like it or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tahini sauce is an all-purpose garnish, which imparts a rich creaminess to whatever it adorns. One of my go-to meals is the “Drbr Tahini Special”, which consists of various roasted vegetables served with rice and topped with giant dollops of this sauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also make a thin version (by adding more water), which can be drizzled on a wide variety of foods (such as &lt;a href=&quot;/entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew/&quot;&gt;lamb stew&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A note about tahini:&lt;/strong&gt; The consistency of tahini can vary widely by brand. The only brand I’ve been disappointed with is Trader Joe’s; it’s much too thick. My family uses the “Al Kanater” brand with the distinctive orange lid, which can be found at Arab grocery stores, although any of the brands found at an Arab store should work equally well. The dense solids settle to the bottom of the jar in storage, so the tahini should be mixed well before pouring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Sauce" /><summary type="html">This sauce is so simple it doesn’t really lend itself to a formal recipe, but I still have to tell you how to make it somehow and this blog template formats every page as a recipe whether I like it or not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arab-American Beef Stew</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arab-American Beef Stew" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew/">&lt;p&gt;One of the mainstay meals of my childhood was “beef cubes and rice”, which was one of my &lt;em&gt;absolute most favorite&lt;/em&gt; things that my mother and grandmother cooked.
It turns out that this is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://redcipes.com/recipe/egyptian-lahma-bil-basal-beef-in-rich-onion-sauce-chaka/&quot;&gt;Lahma Bil Basal&lt;/a&gt;, an Egyptian slow-cooked stew of beef and onions.
As a kid, I thought the rice was the entrée and the beef stew was the side, and although I liked the flavor, I didn’t like the soggy onions in the sauce; so I would strain out the sauce and eat a small pile of dry beef cubes upon a mountain of rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I moved out of my parents’ house, I wanted to continue eating my favorite meal, but my mom’s recipe was always too onion-heavy for my liking. So I cut back on the onions and replaced them with other vegetables, including my newest favorite ingredient, the poblano pepper, which I now use instead of green bell pepper in almost every recipe. Although I grew up eating it with beef, I often make it with lamb instead.
The flavor of lamb is hard to compete with, but beef is denser and holds up better during an extremely long simmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desipite being ethnically inaccurate, I like to cook the stew in a tagine, because it looks more sophisticated.
While I’d be thrilled for you to give my recipe a try, I encourage you to cook the traditional dish as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lambStew-tagine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tagine with lid&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Entrée" /><category term="Middle Eastern" /><summary type="html">One of the mainstay meals of my childhood was “beef cubes and rice”, which was one of my absolute most favorite things that my mother and grandmother cooked. It turns out that this is actually Lahma Bil Basal, an Egyptian slow-cooked stew of beef and onions. As a kid, I thought the rice was the entrée and the beef stew was the side, and although I liked the flavor, I didn’t like the soggy onions in the sauce; so I would strain out the sauce and eat a small pile of dry beef cubes upon a mountain of rice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baba Ghanouj</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baba Ghanouj" /><published>2020-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj/">&lt;p&gt;Baba Ghanouj is a traditional Arabic appetizer, essentially the same thing as hummus but with eggplant instead of chickpeas. Pre-grilled eggplant in a jar can be found at Arab grocery stores, and if this is used, the baba ghanouj can be assembled in mere minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tahini imparts a rich nutty flavor to the dish. I use a lot more of it than many other recipes, and I think it’s an essential component of the taste. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t skimp!&lt;/strong&gt; The recipe says “1 cup”, but I really just pour a bunch in until it looks like there’s enough to smooth out the eggplant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A note about tahini:&lt;/strong&gt; The consistency of tahini can vary widely by brand. The only brand I’ve been disappointed with is Trader Joe’s; it’s much too thick. My family uses the “Al Kanater” brand with the distinctive orange lid (pictured below), which can be found at Arab grocery stores, although any of the brands found at an Arab store should work equally well. The dense solids settle to the bottom of the jar in storage, so the tahini should be mixed well before pouring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tahiniAndEggplant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tahini and eggplant jars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Appetizer" /><category term="Middle Eastern" /><summary type="html">Baba Ghanouj is a traditional Arabic appetizer, essentially the same thing as hummus but with eggplant instead of chickpeas. Pre-grilled eggplant in a jar can be found at Arab grocery stores, and if this is used, the baba ghanouj can be assembled in mere minutes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chespin Brussels Sprouts</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/2019/11/28/chespin-brussels-sprouts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chespin Brussels Sprouts" /><published>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/2019/11/28/chespin-brussels-sprouts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/2019/11/28/chespin-brussels-sprouts/">&lt;p&gt;For those not up to date on the latest video game trends, Chespin is the name of a chestnut-themed Pokémon. I owe this recipe to my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Nate_Buck&quot;&gt;Nate Buck&lt;/a&gt;, enthusiast of video games and gastronomy.
Nate created this recipe using his knowledge of Pokémon along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://karenandandrew.com/books/the-flavor-bible/&quot;&gt;The Flavor Bible&lt;/a&gt;. It was such a big hit at his Pokémon-themed dinner party that I decided to add it to my repertoire as well. I’ve adjusted the recipe slightly, which is how it’s presented here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nate Buck, arr. Andrew Brandon</name></author><category term="Side" /><summary type="html">For those not up to date on the latest video game trends, Chespin is the name of a chestnut-themed Pokémon. I owe this recipe to my friend Nate Buck, enthusiast of video games and gastronomy. Nate created this recipe using his knowledge of Pokémon along with The Flavor Bible. It was such a big hit at his Pokémon-themed dinner party that I decided to add it to my repertoire as well. I’ve adjusted the recipe slightly, which is how it’s presented here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ali Nazik with Chicken</title><link href="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2017/11/10/ali-nazik-chicken/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ali Nazik with Chicken" /><published>2017-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2017/11/10/ali-nazik-chicken</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2017/11/10/ali-nazik-chicken/">&lt;p&gt;Ali Nazik is a Turkish dish, consisting of grilled spiced meat served over a savory eggplant-yogurt sauce. It’s often served alongside rice and salad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ali Nazik” is a Turkish phrase that means “with gentle hands”. The relation of this phrase to the name of the dish is not certain, but one prominent theory is that it refers to the method of making the sauce (don’t make the sauce in the food processor like I did when I wanted to “save time”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to Ali Nazik at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cafe-turko.com/&quot;&gt;Café Turko&lt;/a&gt; in Seattle, where it’s one of the most popular entrées. This is the result of my attempt to reverse-engineer their recipe and adapt it to a home kitchen. The restaurant serves it with either chicken, lamb, or a spicy roasted veggie mix. I’ve only figured out the chicken variety; you’ll have to go there in person to try the others. The owners and staff are all wonderfully friendly and the food is delicious; you won’t regret eating there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like with &lt;a href=&quot;/appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj/&quot;&gt;Baba Ghanouj&lt;/a&gt;, canned grilled eggplant can be used instead of grilling a fresh eggplant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon (inspired by Café Turko)</name></author><category term="Entrée" /><category term="Middle Eastern" /><summary type="html">Ali Nazik is a Turkish dish, consisting of grilled spiced meat served over a savory eggplant-yogurt sauce. It’s often served alongside rice and salad.</summary></entry></feed>