<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-30T21:10:45+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pepper and Olive Oil</title><subtitle>Food blog template for Jekyll.</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;nil}</name></author><entry><title type="html">Arab-American Beef Stew</title><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arab-American Beef Stew" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew/">&lt;p&gt;One of the mainstay meals of my childhood was “beef cubes and rice”, which was one of my &lt;em&gt;absolute most favorite&lt;/em&gt; things that my mother and grandmother cooked.
It turns out that this is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://redcipes.com/recipe/egyptian-lahma-bil-basal-beef-in-rich-onion-sauce-chaka/&quot;&gt;Lahma Bil Basal&lt;/a&gt;, an Egyptian slow-cooked stew of beef and onions.
As a kid, I thought the rice was the entrée and the beef stew was the side, and although I liked the flavor, I didn’t like the soggy onions in the sauce; so I would strain out the sauce and eat a small pile of dry beef cubes upon a mountain of rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I moved out of my parents’ house, I wanted to continue eating my favorite meal, but my mom’s recipe was always too onion-heavy for my liking. So I cut back on the onions and replaced them with other vegetables, including my newest favorite ingredient, the poblano pepper, which I now use instead of green bell pepper in almost every recipe. Although I grew up eating it with beef, I often make it with lamb instead.
The flavor of lamb is hard to compete with, but beef is denser and holds up better during an extremely long simmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desipite being ethnically inaccurate, I like to cook the stew in a tagine, because it looks more sophisticated.
While I’d be thrilled for you to give my recipe a try, I encourage you to cook the traditional dish as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lambStew-tagine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tagine with lid&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><summary type="html">One of the mainstay meals of my childhood was “beef cubes and rice”, which was one of my absolute most favorite things that my mother and grandmother cooked. It turns out that this is actually Lahma Bil Basal, an Egyptian slow-cooked stew of beef and onions. As a kid, I thought the rice was the entrée and the beef stew was the side, and although I liked the flavor, I didn’t like the soggy onions in the sauce; so I would strain out the sauce and eat a small pile of dry beef cubes upon a mountain of rice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tahini Sauce</title><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2020/03/26/tahini-sauce/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tahini Sauce" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2020/03/26/tahini-sauce</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2020/03/26/tahini-sauce/">&lt;p&gt;This sauce is so simple it doesn’t really lend itself to a formal recipe, but I still have to tell you how to make it somehow and this blog template formats every page as a recipe whether I like it or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tahini sauce is an all-purpose garnish, which imparts a rich creaminess to whatever it adorns. One of my go-to meals is the “Drbr Tahini Special”, which consists of various roasted vegetables served with rice and topped with giant dollops of this sauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also make a thin version (by adding more water), which can be drizzled on a wide variety of foods (such as &lt;a href=&quot;/entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2020/03/26/lamb-stew/&quot;&gt;lamb stew&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A note about tahini:&lt;/strong&gt; The consistency of tahini can vary widely by brand. The only brand I’ve been disappointed with is Trader Joe’s; it’s much too thick. My family uses the “Al Kanater” brand with the distinctive orange lid, which can be found at Arab grocery stores, although any of the brands found at an Arab store should work equally well. The dense solids settle to the bottom of the jar in storage, so the tahini should be mixed well before pouring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><summary type="html">This sauce is so simple it doesn’t really lend itself to a formal recipe, but I still have to tell you how to make it somehow and this blog template formats every page as a recipe whether I like it or not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baba Ghanouj</title><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baba Ghanouj" /><published>2020-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj/">&lt;p&gt;Baba Ghanouj is a traditional Arabic appetizer, essentially the same thing as hummus but with eggplant instead of chickpeas. Pre-grilled eggplant in a jar can be found at Arab grocery stores, and if this is used, the baba ghanouj can be assembled in mere minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tahini imparts a rich nutty flavor to the dish. I use a lot more of it than many other recipes, and I think it’s an essential component of the taste. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t skimp!&lt;/strong&gt; The recipe says “1 cup”, but I really just pour a bunch in until it looks like there’s enough to smooth out the eggplant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A note about tahini:&lt;/strong&gt; The consistency of tahini can vary widely by brand. The only brand I’ve been disappointed with is Trader Joe’s; it’s much too thick. My family uses the “Al Kanater” brand with the distinctive orange lid (pictured below), which can be found at Arab grocery stores, although any of the brands found at an Arab store should work equally well. The dense solids settle to the bottom of the jar in storage, so the tahini should be mixed well before pouring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tahiniAndEggplant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tahini and eggplant jars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><summary type="html">Baba Ghanouj is a traditional Arabic appetizer, essentially the same thing as hummus but with eggplant instead of chickpeas. Pre-grilled eggplant in a jar can be found at Arab grocery stores, and if this is used, the baba ghanouj can be assembled in mere minutes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chespin Brussels Sprouts</title><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/2019/11/28/chespin-brussels-sprouts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chespin Brussels Sprouts" /><published>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/2019/11/28/chespin-brussels-sprouts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//side/2019/11/28/chespin-brussels-sprouts/">&lt;p&gt;For those not up to date on the latest video game trends, Chespin is the name of a chestnut-themed Pokémon. I owe this recipe to my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Nate_Buck&quot;&gt;Nate Buck&lt;/a&gt;, enthusiast of video games and gastronomy.
Nate created this recipe using his knowledge of Pokémon along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://karenandandrew.com/books/the-flavor-bible/&quot;&gt;The Flavor Bible&lt;/a&gt;. It was such a big hit at his Pokémon-themed dinner party that I decided to add it to my repertoire as well. I’ve adjusted the recipe slightly, which is how it’s presented here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nate Buck, arr. Andrew Brandon</name></author><summary type="html">For those not up to date on the latest video game trends, Chespin is the name of a chestnut-themed Pokémon. I owe this recipe to my friend Nate Buck, enthusiast of video games and gastronomy. Nate created this recipe using his knowledge of Pokémon along with The Flavor Bible. It was such a big hit at his Pokémon-themed dinner party that I decided to add it to my repertoire as well. I’ve adjusted the recipe slightly, which is how it’s presented here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ali Nazik with Chicken</title><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2017/11/10/ali-nazik-chicken/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ali Nazik with Chicken" /><published>2017-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2017/11/10/ali-nazik-chicken</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/middle%20eastern/2017/11/10/ali-nazik-chicken/">&lt;p&gt;Ali Nazik is a Turkish dish, consisting of grilled spiced meat served over a savory eggplant-yogurt sauce. It’s often served alongside rice and salad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ali Nazik” is a Turkish phrase that means “with gentle hands”. The relation of this phrase to the name of the dish is not certain, but one prominent theory is that it refers to the method of making the sauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to Ali Nazik at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cafe-turko.com/&quot;&gt;Café Turko&lt;/a&gt; in Seattle, where it’s one of the most popular entrées. This is the result of my attempt to reverse-engineer their recipe and adapt it to a home kitchen. The restaurant serves it with either chicken, lamb, or a spicy roasted veggie mix. I’ve only figured out the chicken variety; you’ll have to go there in person to try the others. The owners and staff are all wonderfully friendly and the food is delicious; you won’t regret eating there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like with &lt;a href=&quot;/appetizer/middle%20eastern/2020/01/08/baba-ghanouj/&quot;&gt;Baba Ghanouj&lt;/a&gt;, canned grilled eggplant can be used instead of grilling a fresh eggplant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon (adapted from Café Turko)</name></author><summary type="html">Ali Nazik is a Turkish dish, consisting of grilled spiced meat served over a savory eggplant-yogurt sauce. It’s often served alongside rice and salad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Béchamel Sauce</title><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2012/05/12/bechamel-sauce/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Béchamel Sauce" /><published>2012-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2012/05/12/bechamel-sauce</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//sauce/2012/05/12/bechamel-sauce/">&lt;p&gt;A core component of my &lt;a href=&quot;/entr%C3%A9e/2012/05/12/macaroni-and-cheese/&quot;&gt;Macaroni and Cheese&lt;/a&gt;, the recipe for this sauce was given to me by my brother, Richard Brandon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard provides the following note along with his recipe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also known as white sauce, Béchamel is one of the mother sauces of French cuisine and is also used in many recipes of Italian cuisine.
According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larousse_Gastronomique&quot;&gt;Larousse Gastronomique&lt;/a&gt;, the sauce is named after the “marquis de Béchamel”.
Many other sauces can be made by expanding this recipe.
Grated cheese added brings us a Mornay sauce.
Cooking shrimp shells in the heated milk offers extra flavor to shrimp pasta.
Partial chicken or fish stock can be substituted for the milk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Brandon</name></author><summary type="html">A core component of my Macaroni and Cheese, the recipe for this sauce was given to me by my brother, Richard Brandon.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Macaroni and Cheese au Gratin</title><link href="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/2012/05/12/macaroni-and-cheese/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Macaroni and Cheese au Gratin" /><published>2012-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/2012/05/12/macaroni-and-cheese</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.pepperandoliveoil.com//entr%C3%A9e/2012/05/12/macaroni-and-cheese/">&lt;p&gt;This recipe won 4th place out of 8 in my friends’ Mac and Cheese contest!
That may not sound so impressive, but my friends are really good cooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many macaroni and cheese recipes, this one is based on a &lt;a href=&quot;/sauce/2012/05/12/bechamel-sauce/&quot;&gt;Béchamel Sauce&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Brandon</name></author><summary type="html">This recipe won 4th place out of 8 in my friends’ Mac and Cheese contest! That may not sound so impressive, but my friends are really good cooks.</summary></entry></feed>